Today's דף *Daf* is דף ד *Daf Dalet*. We are still in
the middle of הכל hakol. *Hakol* when it says everybody and mentions
כהן לוי וישראל Kohen Levi v'Yisrael? *Kohen Levi V'Yisrael*, why does it
have to mention כהן לוי וישראל kohein levi ve'yisrael *Kohen Levi V'Yisrael*?
So we have a little bit more of this before we finally
return to the major themes of our theme. So let's take a
look now at the two dots, four lines from the top. הכל
hakol חייבין במקרא מגילה *Hakol chayavin bemikra megilla* by the two dots.
Everybody is obligated to read the מגילה *Megilla*. כהנים לויים וישראלים kohanim,
leviyim, ve'yisraelim. *Kohanim Levi'im v'Yisraelim*. כהנים Kohanim לויים Levi'im, וישראל *Kohanim Levi'im
v'Yisrael*. פשיטא pshita, *Peshita*, obviously, right? לא צריכא לבטל עבודתם *Lo, tzricha
levatel avodatam*. To tell you that even the כהנים Kohanim *Kohanim* would
even leave their עבודה *avoda* in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash. *Beit
HaMikdash* in order to hear מקרא מגילה *Mikra Megilla*. וכדרב יהודה אמר
שמואל *U'kh'd'Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel*. Like רב יהודה אמר שמואל *Rav Yehuda
amar Shmuel*. דאמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל *D'amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel*,
רב יהודה אמר שמואל *Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel* said, כהנים Kohanim בעבודתם
ולויים בדוכנם וישראל במעמדם *Kohanim b'avodatam v'Levi'im b'duchanam v'Yisrael b'ma'amadam*. Even if
everybody is there in the middle of the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash
*Beit HaMikdash*, the כהנים Kohanim *Kohanim* are doing the עבודה *avoda*, the
לויים *Levi'im* are on their דוכן *duchan* doing their singing, the ישראל
Yisrael *Yisrael* is in their מעמד *ma'amad*, which is, it would be
a representation from בני ישראל Bnei Yisroel *Bnei Yisrael* to be present
at the קרבנות Korbanos, *korbanot* because the קרבן Korban *korban*, the communal
קרבנות Korbanos *korbanot* were there for the people, so there was a
representation of the people. So even if you have this drawing this
very beautiful scene last time we saw of which was when there
was a בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash *Beit HaMikdash*, even if you have
this scene that everybody was there doing their עבודה *avoda*, מבטלין עבודתן
ובאין לשמוע מקרא מגילה *mevatlin avodatan u'va'in lishmoa mikra megilla*. They would
stop the עבודה *avoda* and come to hear the reading of the
מגילה *Megilla*. Now what is the reason for this?
So, you know, and I mean it's very rare that we hear
this, like everybody is in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash? *Beit HaMikdash*
and you all leave to go and do מקרא מגילה *Mikra Megilla*.
Or you go and leave to do a מצוה *mitzvah*. So a
couple of things come to mind why the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* sort
of emphasized it to this degree, especially because when רב יהודה *Rav
Yehuda* was talking there was no longer a בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash.
*Beit HaMikdash*, so clearly it was all theoretical, why sort of to
draw it this graphically and underscore to this degree. So there's a
couple of possibilities. One is to emphasize the aspect of פרסומי ניסא
*pirsumei nisa*, right? That פרסומי ניסא *pirsumei nisa*, publicizing the miracle, is
very central, particularly to מגילה *Megilla* and to חנוכה *Chanukah*, as we
said, we say the ברכה bracha *beracha* of שעשה נסים לאבותינו *she'asa
nissim l'avoteinu* when we do that מצוה *mitzvah*. So whereas חנוכה *Chanukah*
though is done each person in their own household and at night
and there's not much as much this sense about public and it's
not at the daytime, מקרא מגילה *Mikra Megilla* is done at sort
of very much at the public level with people being together. And
although we focus on the מגילה *Megilla* reading at night, the primary
מצוה *mitzvah* as far as the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* and the משנה
mishna. *Mishnah* is concerned is during the day. So one might just
be to underscore the aspect of פרסומי ניסא *pirsumei nisa*, it's so
important that we want everybody involved and everybody involved at the same
time and everything else has to take a back seat to that.
That's one reason why we might be underscoring it. Another reason that
occurs to me is, you know, that the נסא *nesa* of the
מגילה *Megilla* happened right in the previous period exactly when it happened,
I'm not going to get exactly right now to the history, but
right around the time when the second בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash, *Beit
HaMikdash* was about to be rebuilt, being rebuilt and so on. So,
you know, you might have wanted to frame it that well, the
purpose of the נסא *nesa* of מגילה *Megilla* was that it allowed
the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash, *Beit HaMikdash* to be rebuilt, you know,
and frame it in the sense in the context of sort of
like we sort of frame חנוכה *Chanukah*, you know, that it was
about the dedication of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash *Beit HaMikdash* and
so on, חנוכה *Chanukah* is also about a lot more. But anyway,
you might have wanted to frame it in the context of the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash, *Beit HaMikdash* and therefore say well, so if
you're really doing the עבודה *avoda* in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash.
*Beit HaMikdash* that shouldn't take a back seat. Obviously now that we
no longer have a בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash. *Beit HaMikdash*, you know,
it is not helpful to frame the נסא *nesa* of מגילה *Megilla*
only in that sense. And anyway, we clearly know that the נסא
*nesa* of the מגילה *Megilla* was much broader, it really was the,
you know, that was the time when they were not just out
to destroy the Jewish religion but the Jewish people and therefore, you
know, it has a meaning that much more sort of transcends that
of the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash, *Beit HaMikdash*. So anyway, those are
just like two thoughts about why we actually make this very graphic
description, but the basic point is is that this is a מצוה
*mitzvah* of פרסומי ניסא *pirsumei nisa* and therefore, you know, everything takes
a back seat and that's why we mention כהן Kohen לוי Levi
וישראל *Kohen Levi V'Yisrael*. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* goes
on and says the following: הכל hakol חייבין בזימון *Hakol chayavin b'zimmun*,
we're back to זימון Zimun. *zimmun*. Everybody is obligated in זימון Zimun
*zimmun*,
כהנים Kohanim,
לויים וישראלים *Kohanim Levi'im v'Yisraelim*, כהן Kohen לוי Levi. וישראל *Kohen Levi
V'Yisrael*. פשיטא Pshita *Peshita*, obviously. לא צריכא דאכלי קדשים *Lo, tzricha d'akhli
kodshim*. That let's say the כהנים kohanim *Kohanim* are eating their קרבנות
Korbanos, *korbanot*, and now before we get to mixing with ישראל *Yisrael*,
let's just say three כהנים kohanim *Kohanim* together that are eating קרבנות
Korbanos *korbanot*, obviously with bread because we're making a זימון Zimun *zimmun*.
So maybe they wouldn't make a זימון Zimun *zimmun*, why not? סלקא
דעתך אמינא salka dachatch amina, *Salta da'atakh amina*, I might have thought,
אכלו אותם אשר כופר בהם אמר רחמנא *akhlu otam asher kuppar bahem
amar Rachmana*. They should eat it that have achieved atonement through them.
And we learn from there that when the כהנים kohanim eat the
קרבנות, Korbanos it achieves atonement for בני ישראל who brought the sacrifices.
So therefore what? Therefore I might think that the eating of the
קרבנות Korbanos is not focused on normally when you eat, it's because
you got sustenance, you got satisfied, it serves sort of your, you
know, physical needs as a human being, and therefore you thank God.
But if you're a כהן kohen who's eating the קרבנות, korbanot if
the concept of כהנים kohanim. eating the קרבנות korbanot are that they're
representing as it were God, the altar, their consumption is like the
consumption of the altar, so maybe we don't focus on them as,
you know, as personal as people who are physically benefiting from it.
They're doing a ritual act and therefore maybe it's not appropriate even
to do a ברכת המזון Birchas Hamazon which makes it very much
like they're just filling their bellies and it doesn't make it as
much as the sort of eating of the altar, the eating in
the sort of the consumption that's done in the בית המקדש. So
I might think that you do not necessarily do a זימון. Zimun
והא כפרה היא V'ha kapara hi and this is just a כפרה.
kapara. קא משמע לן Ka mashma lan ואכלת ושבעת אמר
רחמנא V'achalta v'savata amar rachmana you eat and be satisfied, and that's
still true, they're still filling their bellies even if that's not the
primary way to define it. Now this is interesting, curious, for, I
mean number one, what's the conclusion? Is the conclusion that the way
we look at them eating their קרבנות korbanot is not just in
this way as if the altar is consuming it, but actually when
the כהנים Kohanim get what their קרבנות korbanot is also a type
of a payment or gift to them for their service? And therefore
there's also that sense of sort of taking it for their personal
needs, they're not just consuming it like the altar consumes it. That's
one way. Or the other way is no, even if the act
we look at as as it were consumption of the altar and
that's primarily how we frame the act of their eating, nevertheless if
you have if you do derive actual benefit you still are going
to do a ברכת המזון Birchas Hamazon even if that was not
the fundamental framing of what you did. The very fact that you
actually set got this benefit requires you to give thanks, requires you
to do ברכת המזון. Birchas Hamazon. So again the question I'm raising
is whether the conclusion is telling us to reframe the way we
think of the act of eating it, or even if we're not
reframing it, since in the end they did actually benefit, therefore that
requires a ברכת המזון Birchas Hamazon even if that's not the fundamental
framing. Yes, Rivka.
I think
this talks about זימון Zimun not ברכת המזון. Birchas Hamazon. זימון Zimun
is different than ברכת המזון. Birchas Hamazon. זימון Zimun is three people
forming a group, so that if they ate each one individually. Right,
so how we imagine the כהנים Kohanim each one is doing the
קרבן korban and eating individually. זימון Zimun. is talking about a group.
Right, so it is true that I would
have
agreed with you but then it's not clear why the fact that
it's a כפרה kapara and the quoting of the פסוק pasuk of
ואכלת ושבעת V'achalta v'savata is responding to the aspect of זימון Zimun.
which is an aspect of sort of צירוף, tzeruf, you know, coming
together and קבע keva and how that's being addressed by why
why it would have thought differently because of כפרה kapara and why
ואכלת V'achalta is a response to that.
Unless you're saying they're equating זימון Zimun with ברכת המזון Birchas Hamazon
or they say זימון Zimun. but they really mean ברכת המזון. Birchas
Hamazon. But it says זימון.
Zimun, I understand. The next phrase is going to be מצטרפין לזימון
mitztarfin l'zimun and that is זימון. Zimun. You know, my understanding here
and I my initial reading would have been like you, but given
the way the גמרא Gemara quotes the פסוקים, psukim, my understanding was
here that it was saying זימון Zimun as let me say let
me just take a look at what רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom says,
רש"י. Rashi.
Yeah, I mean like actually there's an interesting גרסא girsa in the
רבינו גרשום. Rabbeinu Gershom. He says I might have thought that you
would not need have needed a ברכה bracha and then they take
out the word ברכה and they insert the word זימון. zimmun So,
you know, I agree with you but in the next line the
גמרא's Gemara going to focus on sort of coming together as a
זימון, zimmun so it seems that the גמרא Gemara is reading this
as as a ברכת המזון, Birchas Hamazon, but we'll we'll see the
next line where it really reads it in the context of זימון.
zimmun Yes.
And I'm just wondering whether the fact that the כהן kohen, have
to give blessings is is again to show the people that they're
not God.
I mean I think it's a
very very lofty beings who have so much power.
Meaning the flip side, right, the flip side of not wanting to
frame this as just filling your belly is you don't want to,
you know, you don't want the כהנים Kohanim to too much identify
with, you know, you know, that that they are total representatives of
God. They're still human.
Especially for themselves, yes,
and very much for themselves, which is precious, but also for the
masses, for the people, that they're not worshipping the כהנים, Kohanim they're
the representatives.
Right. I think that's a very good point. I have to tell
you by the way the one thing that I'm bothered with here
is that is that ברכת המזון Birchas Hamazon or a זימון zimmun?
either way is only with
bread and there is... And the קרבנות are primarily meat although there
are also and you say they're eating bread with it but then
that's not what the obligat—that's not—but but it could be that the
מנחות, menachot, the מנחות. menachot. I
don't think the same is true about any אכילת כהנים achilat kohanim
which includes the אכילה achila of the מנחות. menachot. So it could
be that it's including the אכילה achila of the מנחות, menachot, but
it is interesting that the גמרא Gemara does not spell it out.
Yes.
I mean, it's funny because it's ואכלו ve'achalu though. Then the answer
is ואכלת ושבעת, ve'achalta vesavata, you know? So like, I'm still not
understanding exactly.
So I said, either it's telling you that even if it is
framed as an act of, as a ritual act and an act
of כפרה, kapara, the reality that you derived benefit is still obligate,
or it's saying that there's two things going on here. There's, you
know, which is both an act of, a ritual act and also
they're also entitled to view it as, you know, their own type
of sustenance. So it's a question of does it change how we
frame the act, or even if we haven't framed the act differently,
there still is the reality of having derived benefit as מחייב ברכת
המזון. mechayev Birkat Hamazon.
I'm trying to struggle with the הוה אמינא. hava amina. Let's say
I brought my שלמים, shelamim, it's also a ritual act, would then
the הוה אמינא hava amina be I'm exempt because it's some sort
of ritual?
No, no, no. The eating is not, has not been redefined. If
the fundamental eating of the כהנים Kohanim is like an eating of
the מזבח mizbeach and they're representing it's almost God or the altar
and so on, and that's why it achieves כפרה, kapara, then you
don't view them as just filling their belly. Okay, let's take a
look. The גמרא Gemara continues: הכל מצטרפין לזימון. hakol mitztarfin lezimmun. Now
this is the issue about really making a זימון zimmun. and coming
together as three. כהנים Kohanim, לויים וישראלים. פשיטא, pshita,
obviously they can all combine, especially since now we've sort of sidelined
the קרבן korban as a significant, as being reframed. לא צריכא דקאכלי
כהנים תרומה. lo tzricha dekachli kohanim teruma.
Now we're not talking about קרבנות now, we've put that aside, but
let's say that they're eating תרומה teruma או קדשים, o kodashim, but
not because it's not a normal אכילה, achila, it is a normal
אכילה. achila. The only problem is that what the כהנים Kohanim are
eating, they cannot ask the ישראל and the לוי Levi to join
in with them. They're eating things that only כהנים Kohanim are able
to eat. Okay, so therefore וזר לא יאכל וכולי, ve'zar lo yochal
ve'chulei, and the non-כהן kohen is eating חולין, chullin, you know, not
sanctified food. סלקא דעתך אמינא, salkadaitach amina, I might have thought, הואיל
ואי בעי זר למיכל בהדי כהן לא מצי אכיל, ho'il ve'i ba'ei
zar lemichal bahadi kohen lo matzi achil, that he cannot, if the
זר zar wanted to join in with the כהן, kohen, the כהן
kohen cannot have him have some of his
food because his food can only be eaten by כהנים. Kohanim So
therefore, אימא לא ליצטרף, eima lo litzteref,
maybe you can't consider them a group because they're not able to
share the same food. קא משמע לן, ka mashma lan, הי דזר
בהדי כהן לא מצי אכיל, hei de'zar bahadi kohen lo matzi achil,
so it's teaching us that although it's true that the זר zar
can't eat with the כהן, Kohen כהן בהדי זר מצי אכיל, kohen
bahadi zar matzi achil, the כהן Kohen can eat with the זר
zar and therefore it is considered a group.
Now that leaves—not enough to go around for everyone?
Yeah, that's not the issue. The issue is in theory can you
consider it a, like one type of an eating. So since they
all could be sharing some of the food, at least in theory,
that's one type of an eating. Now that leads תוספות Tosafot to
have an interesting question about are there scenarios in where nobody can
eat from anybody else's. So תוספות Tosafot for example wants to say,
let's say everybody made a נדר, neder, a vow, that I can't
benefit from you, which you might think that the very act that
we've made that vow defines us as sort of a little bit
at war with one another and not as a unified group. Anyway,
so תוספות Tosafot says maybe that wouldn't be an issue because maybe
in theory you could always get a היתר heter for your נדר,
neder, but the more common case that comes up actually in הלכה
halacha where this is true is מילכיגס ופליישיגס. milchigs u'fleishigs. If I'm
eating מילכיגס milchigs and you're eating פליישיגס, fleishigs, so as soon as
I am, you know,
I've taken a bite of my פליישיגס, fleishigs, after that moment, you
know, maybe before we started I could have, we could have all
eaten with you, but after that moment I can't eat with you,
you're having the מילכיגס. milchigs. So the actual הלכה halacha is that
we are able to make a זימון because the guy eating מילכיגס
milchigs could in theory just wash out his mouth, although some people
wait a half hour, whatever, but in theory he could just wash
out his mouth and eat with the פליישיגס, fleishigs, although they say
that the person who leads the זימון should be the guy eating
מילכיגס milchigs because he's at least the one that has the ability
to join with the others, not in the other direction. But you
could think of other scenarios, let's say he's eating hard cheese and
following the מנהג minhag of, you know, waiting six hours after hard
cheese. Let's say there's cases about somebody being, you know, having different
types of physical intolerances and not הלכתית halachically can't eat, but you
know, lactose intolerant, other types of, you know, gluten, other types of
things. So, you know, do those create problems for creating a צירוף
tzeruf for a זימון? And that is really is discussed in הלכה.
halacha. Certainly the principle here that as long as one person can
combine is enough to create the צירוף, tzeruf, that we say, and
but if there are הלכתי halachic barriers and nobody can combine with
anybody else, you do not make a זימון. If it's physical issues,
health issues, not הלכתי halachic issues, that's more discussed, but that's a
serious possibility that that would also say that you can't consider it
as though it's sort of one joint type of an eating. Okay,
so now we continue. So that's the issue about what the חידוש
chiddush of מצטרפין לזימון, mitztarfin lezimmun, that really was a חידוש chiddush
with very relevant הלכתי halachic implications. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
continues: הכל מעריכין. hakol maarichin.
Now the issue— So we finally return back to our משנה. mishna
If you would you know it was almost like a little bit
of a chiastic structure not exactly but you know it starts with
הכל. hakol What does הכל hakol come to include? So we go
through all the הכל we start with our משנה mishna but we
go through all the הכל that we can that we pull together.
Then we say why does it say כהן Kohen לוי Levi וישראל?
So then we start from the non-משנה mishna. cases and then we
finally come back and end with our משנה. mishna Why does our
משנה mishna. say הכל מעריכין כהן לוי וישראל? hakol maarichin Kohen Levi
v'Yisrael? So now we're back to our משנה. mishna. Okay. פשיטא obviously
everybody could be מעריך maariach except the obligation to give a donation
to the בית המקדש based on somebody's value. אמר רבא לא נצרכה
אלא לבן בוכרי. Amar Rava lo nitzrecha ela l'Ben Buchri.
It's only required for to tell me to respond to the position
of בן בוכרי. Ben Buchri. Now we're talking about a משנה. mishna.
This is in שקלים. Shekalim.
Where is it?
Or actually it's in שקלים Shekalim but it might also be in
ערכין Arachin or מנחות. Menachot. Hold on. מנחות. Menachot. I have it.
Whatever. Anyway, okay here's the משנה. Mishnah
אמר רבי יהודה העיד בן בוכרי. Amar Rabbi Yehuda he'id Ben Buchri.
בן בוכרי Ben Buchri testified ביבנה. b'Yavne. ביבנה b'Yavne was when after
the בית המקדש was destroyed when they sort of started recording all
of the תורה שבעל פה Torah she-be'al peh and people came and
gave testimonies. So he gave the following testimony ביבנה. b'Yavne. שכל כהן
ששוקל אינו חוטא. She-kol Kohen she-shokel eino chotei. If a כהן Kohen,
wants to give the שקל, shekel, the half of the שקל shekel
each year, it's not a sin. It's not a problem. He's not
obligated but if he wants to give the donation he's able. We'll
see why in a minute why he's not obligated and what might
have been a problem for him to give. But implicitly he's basically
saying כהנים kohanim. do not have to give the half שקל. shekel.
אמר לו רבן יוחנן בן זכאי. Amar lo Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai.
רבן יוחנן בן זכאי Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai said to him לא
כן. lo chen. That's not the הלכה. halacha. אלא כל כהן שאינו
שוקל חוטא. Ela kol Kohen she-eino shokel chotei.
It's the opposite. If you don't give the half שקל shekel you're
sinning. Meaning it's not like you don't have to but if you
give it it's okay. It's actually that you have to. If you
don't give it you're doing something wrong. Every כהן kohen has to
give the half שקל. shekel. אלא Ela why do כהנים kohanim, think
that they don't? שהכהנים דורשים מקרא זה לעצמן. She-ha-Kohanim dorshim mikra zeh
l'atzman.
They read the following verse in their own self-interest. Towards what how
do they read the verse? וכל מנחת כהן כליל תהיה לא תאכל.
V'chol minchat Kohen kalil tihyeh lo te'achel.
Every מנחה mincha of a כהן kohen, shall be completely burned, it
cannot be eaten. So therefore the כהנים kohanim say ah this is
going to be how we're going to get out of having to
give the half שקל. shekel. Because the הלכה halacha is that any
מנחה mincha that we own has to be burned. But there are
some מנחות menachot that are communal מנחות menachot that we know aren't
burned. And if we're going to own a part of them that's
going to change their הלכה. halacha. That's going to demand that they
be burned. So here's what they said. הואיל ואומר ושתי הלחם ולחם
הפנים. Ho'il v'omer u-shtei ha-lechem v'lechem ha-panim. Here are communal מנחות. menachot.
The עומר Omer brought on the second day of פסח, Pesach, the
שתי הלחם shtei ha-lechem brought on שבועות, Shavuot, and the לחם הפנים,
lechem ha-panim, the bread that is brought every day on שבת. Shabbat.
Those are all you know sort of flour water offerings מנחות. menachot.
And the הלכה halacha is that they're eaten and they're communal. Now
the whole idea of the half שקל shekel is to be a
partner in the communal sacrifices. So they said שלנו הם. shelanu hem.
If we were to give the half שקל shekel they would we
would be a part owner. והיאך נאכלים? v'heich ne'echalim?
How could they be eaten? So it's we just care for the
rest of כלל ישראל. Klal Yisrael. We don't want our ownership to
have to change the status of these קרבנות and it would not
be actually you know and and therefore we're not going to be
partners in the קרבנות because or else that would actually you know
make these מנחות menachot not able to be eaten. And so רבן
יוחנן בן זכאי Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai says that's what they say
but that's not the הלכה. halacha. The הלכה halacha is they have
to contribute for the obvious reason that that is not a מנחת
כהנים minchat Kohanim just because they have a part ownership. Now that
by the way is framed two ways. Number one is that it's
only מנחת כהנים minchat Kohanim if they're 100% owners not if they're
5% owners. You know not if their ownership is not complete. But
the other way the even the more satisfying way is that a
communal sacrifice is not a partnership. We've discussed this before that הלכה
halacha really does not have so much of a sense of a
corporate entity of a corporation. It really only knows about partnerships. But
here and there it does have a sense of an abstract entity.
One is יורשים yorshim that inherit an estate. And the other is
this concept of ציבור. tzibbur. Although millions of individuals give a half
שקל shekel in the end it's not that everybody is a point
point point zero one percent partner. It's that this is now owned
by the community you know that the the the representative the corporate
entity that is the ציבור. tzibbur. And therefore even if the כהנים
kohanim. are part of that ציבור tzibbur they're not considered you know
person it's not considered their קרבן korban even part owners. It's owned
by the ציבור tzibbur as an entire as an entire corporate entity.
Now it is interesting though the idea that they דורשים מקרא זה
לעצמן dorshim mikra zeh l'atzman because you know that's in a way
it's it's an easy trap to fall in for somebody that actually
is like you know a rabbi in the שול shul or something
that you basically feel you know hey you know I work for
the שול shul here why should I have to make a donation
to the שול? shul? You know I'm you know the שול'ס shul's
paying me and I'm doing all this work for why should I
be the one to make to make the donation? Rabbi Weiss you
know once said that for one of the things that הרב סולובייצ'יק
Rav Soloveitchik said to him when he was going out for to
become a rabbi, one of the few things he said is, make
sure, you know, you're always there for מנין, minyan, and make sure
you're the first to donate at an appeal. Because it's very easy,
you know, as the rabbi to think, oh, why do I have
to be for מנין? minyan? I'm there every single all the time.
Why do I have to give to an appeal? They're paying me,
I'm not paying them, you know, and so on. So it's, you
know, the כהנים kohanim sort of feel, why should we give to
the בית המקדש? You know, we're serving, we're already doing all of
our work for the בית המקדש. Anyway, so that's what רבן יוחנן
בן זכאי Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai says, that that's their self-interest, but
that's actually not the הלכה. halacha. So they do have to give.
But now בן בוכרי Ben Buchri says actually that they don't give.
So let's understand בן בוכרי. Ben Buchri. Let's take a look. They're
not obligated to give. So he says like this.
בן בוכרי נמי, Ben Buchri nami, according to בן בוכרי, Ben Buchri,
כיון דלכתחילה לא מיחייבי לאתויי, keivan delichatchila lo michayvei le'asuyei,
let's understand בן בוכרי. Ben Buchri. If you're saying that they're not
obligated to give because, you know, maybe, now he doesn't exactly say
why, but it seems that it's not just based on the fact
they work in the בית המקדש, it seems that he excludes the
entire tribe of לוי. Levi You know, it's an interesting point that
we, that when the תורה Torah counts the 12 tribes, it's always
12, although who are the 12 are not always the same. Sometimes
לוי Levi is counted, and יוסף Yosef and בנימין Binyamin
and אפרים Ephraim and מנשה Menashe are counted as one as יוסף.
Yosef. Sometimes לוי Levi is not counted and אפרים Ephraim and מנשה
Menashe are two. But you could certainly say that, you know, in
some ways, לוי Levi, because of their special role and function or
whatever as the priestly or לוי class or whatever, are not necessarily,
you know,
defined as one of the primary 12 tribes. So maybe בן בוכרי
Ben Buchri is saying, because this is elsewhere we see that it's
not just the כהנים, kohanim it includes לוי as well, whatever. Anyway,
that, that, that, that yes, you can have represent corporate כלל ישראל
Klal Yisrael with the other 12 tribes without לוי, therefore they don't
have to give and it still is the קרבן korban, of כלל
ישראל. Klal Yisrael. And again, maybe similar to the פסוקים pesukim quoted,
the idea that there are people that bring, that offer the קרבן,
korban and then there are people that actually do the work in
the בית המקדש, and those are different classes of people. So therefore
you do not participate in the מחצית השקל. machatzis hashekel. So if
that's true, then why if they want to give, are they able
to give? So let's take a look. So since they're not at
the outset obligated, כי מייתי נמי, ki mayisei nami, if you do
choose to bring, חוטא הוא, chotei hu, you should be a sinner,
דמאיחולין לזרה, de'maichulin lezarah, because then part of the sacrifices are not
fully, are not fully sanctified. You have a part ownership in the
sacrifice, but it's not real, it's not a real donation to the
temple, so it's not really fully sanctified, right? It's not really, normally
if you have to give, then your money becomes sanctified and the
sacrifices are communal. But if you don't have to give, maybe it's
your personal ownership that's taking, that's there. So the גמרא gemara says,
no, דמייתי להו מסרו לציבור. demaisei lehu masru litzibbur. When you give
your donation, we assume you are fully giving it, although I'm not
obligated to give, if you're choosing to give, you fully give over
your money to the בית המקדש and therefore it is fully, the
money is sanctified and the קרבן korban. is sanctified and owned by
כלל ישראל, Klal Yisrael, not you, the כהן, kohen, maintaining some personal
ownership. So therefore, according to בן בוכרי, Ben Buchri, that the כהנים
kohanim are not obligated, going back to the מחצית השקל, machatzis hashekel,
now we come back to our משנה Mishnah about
ערכין. Arachin.
סלקא דעתך אמינא, salkadaitach amina, מחצית השקל machatzis hashekel and to give
it over to the ציבור tzibbur then.
I just said the reasons about how exactly you count the 12
tribes, different classes of who brings and who offers. Okay, so let's
just think, סלקא דעתך אמינא, salka daitach amina, I would have thought,
הואיל וכתיב, ho'il uksiv, the verse says, וכל ערכך יהיה בשקל הקדש,
vechol erkecha yiheyeh beshekel hakodesh,
that every, your ערך erech should be in the מחצית השקל. machatzis
hashekel. This is the ערך erech when you give the values that
our משנה's Mishnah talking about. How do you determine how much? Five
שקל shekel for this, three שקל shekel for that, 50 שקל shekel
for that. It's all in the שקלים shekels of the בית המקדש,
that's a verse. I would have said because it's comparing ערך erech
to שקל, shekel, I would have said the following thing. כל דאיתא
בשקלים איתא
בערכין, kol de'isa bishkalim isa be'erchin, anybody that's in the category of
giving the שקלים shkalim is in the category of giving ערכין. erchin.
והני כהנים הואיל וליתנהו בשקלים, vehani Kohanim ho'il velaisnu bishkalim, and since
we've just said that the כהנים kohanim. are not in the שקלים,
shkalim, ליתנהו בערכין, laisnu be'erchin,
they're not also in ערכין. erchin. So I might have thought that
according to בן בוכרי, Ben Buchri, they don't give the מחצית השקל,
machatzis hashekel, they're also not in the category of ערך, erech, because
ערך erech is linked to שקל. shekel. So קא משמע לן, kamashmalan,
so therefore our משנה Mishnah is teaching me that even so, כהנים
give the, can do an ערך, erech, if they obligate themselves in
an ערך, erech, they are obligated. Okay, so that's, it was a
long explanation, but basically because according to one opinion they're not in
the מחצית השקל, machatzis hashekel, I might have thought they were excluded.
That was answer number one. אמר ליה אביי, amar lei Abaye, to
which אביי Abaye responds, האי וכל ערכך, hai vechol erkecha, that idea
that all of your values shall be in the שקל, shekel, it's
not made to link it to the מחצית השקל. machatzis hashekel. It's
coming for a different דרשה. drasha. לכל ערכין שאתה מעריך לא יפחתו
מסלע דאורייתא. lechol erchin she'atah marich lo yifchasu misela d'oraysa. It's for
a more straightforward point, that a one שקל, shekel, that a שקל
shekel is your minimum unit of currency for the ערך. erech. Now
why do you need to say it? The תורה Torah says the
smallest unit in the תורה Torah actually is three שקל shekel for
a... A baby girl is three שקל. shekel. So what does it
mean your smallest unit is one שקל? shekel? We are going to
see that the תורה Torah also says, although it gives all those
fixed amounts, it also says כפי אשר תשיג יד הנודר יערכנו הכהן.
kefi asher tasig yad hanoder yaarichenu hakohen.
According to the ability of to of the of the one who
vowed to make a payment, that's how the כהן kohen should estimate
it. So from there the גמרא gemara understands that what that's telling
us is is that if you made a vow to give this
person's value and that comes out to five שקל, shekel, fifty שקל,
shekel, whatever, and then actually you got carried away by some spur
of the moment thing and actually you can't afford more than a
שקל. shekel. So then since you're not able to afford more, we
can redetermine how much does it does that translate to based on
your ability to pay. כפי אשר תשיג יד הנודר, kefi asher tasig
yad hanoder, okay? That's השגת יד. hasagat yad. Now
let's say you really can't even pay a שקל, shekel, let's say
the most you can afford is a half שקל, shekel, a quarter
שקל. shekel. That's what we learn from this verse, כל ערכך יהיה
בשקל הקודש, kol erchecha yiheyeh beshekel hakodesh, that no, even though we
have a sliding scale, right, you know this like people say here's
my fee but I have a sliding scale. So here's what the
תורה Torah says, here's the fee but it's a sliding scale. But
the sliding scale has a minimum and the minimum is one שקל.
shekel. That's what we learn from this verse. Okay, so you cannot
learn it to think that only people in the half שקל shekel
are in ערך. erech. It's coming to tell you a more straightforward
הלכה halacha that the sliding scale ends at one שקל. shekel. So
the גמרא gemara says like this, so
אלא אמר אביי, ela amar Abaye, here's why I would have thought
to exclude כהנים. איצטריך, itztarech, you need it. סלקא דעתך אמינא, salka
daitach amina, I would have thought, הוי וכתיב ופדויו מבן חודש
תפדה בערכך. hovei uchtiv upduyav miben chodesh tifdeh beerchecha. Now this is
maybe a better הוה אמינא. hava amina. It says it uses the
same word ערך erech when you do פדיון הבן. pidyon haben. And
not only that, as was pointed out, פדיון הבן pidyon haben is
five שקל, shekel, and also for a boy after after a month,
ערך erech is five שקל, shekel, so there's a conceptual link there.
And the פדיון הבן pidyon haben and it uses the word ערך.
erech. So I might have thought to say כל דאיתא בפדיון הבן
איתא בערכין, kol de'ita bepidyon haben ita beerchin, if you're in the
category of פדיון הבן, pidyon haben, you're in the category of ערכין.
erchin. והני כהנים הואיל וליתנהו בפדיון הבן
ליתנהו בערכין, vehani kohanim ho'il uleitnehu bepidyon haben leitnehu beerchin, but כהנים,
since they do not do פדיון הבן pidyon haben for their own
children, right, and even לויים, and even a בת כהן bat kohen
and a בת לוי, bat Levi, maybe if you're not in the
category of פדיון הבן, pidyon haben, you're not in the category of
ערך, erech, because you have that word ערך erech in the תורה
Torah to link it. קא משמע לן, ka mashma lan, so our
משנה Mishnah is telling you that even כהנים are in that category.
אמר ליה רבא, amar leh Rava, רבא Rava said back to this,
אלא מעתה גבי איל אשם, ela me'ata gabei ayil asham, you can't
say we put that much emphasis on the word ערך, erech, because
then it'll lead to crazy conclusions. We have a ram of an
אשם, asham, a type of a sin offering, דכתיב, dechtiv, the verse
says by that ram, ואת אשמו יביא לה' איל תמים מן הצאן
בערכך, ve'et ashamo yavi l'Hashem ayil tamim min hatzon beerchecha, the sin
offering, the guilt offering you should bring to God,
a ram from the sheep in the value, it has the exact
same word בערכך. beerchecha. And I would have thought to say הכא
נמי, hacha nami, would you have thought to say דכל דאיתא בערכין
איתא באיל אשם, dechol de'ita beerchin ita be'ayil asham,
that you only bring the ram if you're in the category of
ערך? erech? והא טומטום ואנדרוגינוס דליתנהו בערכין, veha tumtum ve'androgynos deleitnehu beerchin,
how about טומטום tumtum and אנדרוגינוס androgynos that our משנה Mishnah that
excludes these people of indeterminate gender from being the objects of an
ערך? erech? So I might say, oh, so this word ערך erech
links, you know, our category to other categories. So if it links
it to פדיון הבן, pidyon haben, and maybe it also links it
to the ram, and I would have said that ליתנהו באיל אשם,
leitnehu be'ayil asham, that these people of indeterminate gender would not bring
this ram? That's impossible, you know, because they if they sinned, regardless
of whether you're you're male or female or or some middle gender,
it shouldn't matter, you have to bring a קרבן. So therefore we
cannot give too much weight to this word בערכך, beerchecha, it proves
too much. It would have led us to exclude other people or
have to deal with other consequences to think that this links and
limits the category of who's obligated. אלא אמר רבא, ela amar Rava,
rather says רבא, Rava, here's why I would have thought to exclude
כהנים. ואי תימא רב אשי, ve'i teima Rav Ashi, some say רב
אשי, Rav Ashi, איצטריך, itztarech, I need it to tell me כהנים
are obligated. סלקא דעתך אמינא, salka da'atach amina
since the verse says והעמידו לפני הכהן, vehe'emido lifnei hakohen, you stand
the person before the כהן, kohen, this is the person who needs
to go on the sliding scale, who cannot pay the amount that
he is fixed, so you stand him in front of the כהן,
kohen the כהן kohen estimates what he's able to pay and gives
a new number. So since it says you stand him before the
כהן, kohen ולא כהן לפני כהן. velo kohen lifnei kohen. And that's
similar to the idea of the half שקל, shekel, meaning there are
different roles. There's the role of the כהן kohein to assess how
much you owe, and then there's you, the non-כהנים that made the
vow. So I might have thought those are different classes, the כהנים
that are involved in assessing and collecting the money and the rest
of the people who are the ones who make the vow. And
I might have said that a כהן cannot be in the role
of the rest of the people, ולא כהן לפני כהן, velo kohen
lifnei kohen, it was just a הוה אמינא. hava amina. I would
have thought to define those as different roles, which was presumably actually
what בן בוכרי Ben Buchri says by the half שקל. shekel. קא
משמע לן ka mashma lan that they don't say that, that yes,
the כהן plays that role, but he could also play the other
role of actually making the vow as well. Okay, so that finally
solves our question in the משנה Mishnah about why the משנה mishna.
had to say that everybody, even כהנים. are obligated in the, if
they make an ערך erech vow, they have to pay. Now we
look at the next part of the משנה. mishna
Okay, קמשמע לן, Kamashma lan, נערכים לאתויי, ne'erachim le'atuyei, what does it
mean that everybody can be נערך? ne'erach? So what's that coming to
include?
לאתויי... Le'atuyei... so now we're done, excuse me, we're done with כהן
לוי ישראל. kohein levi yisrael. We've did what does הכל come to
include, what does כהן לוי וישראל come to include, and now we've
gone through that by our משנה mishna and by in general elsewhere
in ש"ס. shas. Now we are finally going to look case by
case at ערכין erchin and our משנה Mishnah. and understand some of
the parameters. Now you might remember that one of the things the
גמרא gemara says הכל נערכים hakol ne'erachim comes to include is that
even somebody that would never be able to be sold as a
slave and has no market value is still can be an object
of an ערך erech and you pay the fixed value in the
תורה. torah. And now we're going to look at that הלכה. halacha.
Now that we're done with כהן לוי ישראל. kohein levi yisrael. So
let's take a look.
Okay,
where are we?
הכל
נערכים. hakol ne'erachim. I'm sorry, I'm sorry. קמשמע לן, Kamashma lan, נערכים
לאתויי, ne'erachim le'atuyei, what does everybody is נערך ne'erach include? מנוול ומוכת
שחין, menuval u'mukat shechin, somebody who is disgusting and you know filled
with blemishes and warts, somebody that would have no market value. מנא
הני מילי? Mena hani milei? And I might think that because there's
no market value, if you say the value, not the ערך, erech,
but the market value, you don't pay anything, maybe you also wouldn't
be an ערך. erech. No, ערך erech goes by the fixed charts.
Okay, מנא הני מילי, Mena hani milei, where do you know this?
דתנו רבנן, Detanu rabanan, we have a ברייתא. braita. This is going
to be a big ברייתא. braita. We're going to quote the whole
ברייתא braita and then we're going to analyze it. בערכך, Be'erkecha,
according to the value, להביא ערך סתום, lehavi erech satum, that even
if a person did not say the ערך erech of this person.
If you say the ערך erech of this person, you look the
person up on a chart. Let's say you just say the ערך
erech of a person, I will pay. So who? Depends whether male,
female, age, or whatever. So even you might think that person maybe
doesn't pay anything because there's no particular person. No, you still pay.
We'll see in a minute what you do pay, but you still
pay. That you learn out from the word extra word בערכך. be'erkecha.
דבר אחר, Davar acher, another thing we learn out, בערכך, be'erkecha, ערך
כולו הוא נותן ולא ערך איברים, erech kulo hu notein velo erech
evarim, only a full ערך, erech, not a limb. Meaning let's say
you said I will pay the ערך erech of that person's arm.
Now if you said I will pay the value of that person's
arm, you would determine its value again based on this market-based valuation.
How exactly do you do a market-place valuation is you would say,
well, if this person were a slave what would their market value
be? If they were a slave without the arm what would their
market value be? And the difference is the value of the arm.
So that's if you said their value and you just said דמים
damim or you know some other word. But when you say the
word ערך, erech, ערך erech relates to the whole person and if
you say and the fixed value. And if you say ערך erech
of the arm, you don't pay anything. Okay? יכול שאני מוציא אף
דבר שהנשמה תלויה בו, Yachol she'ani motzi af davar she'haneshama tluyah bo,
maybe I'll exclude even something that the soul depends on. Let's say
you said the ערך erech of the brain, the ערך erech of
the heart. תלמוד לומר נפשות, Talmud lomar nefashot,
the souls, which means anything that a life is dependent on. So
if somebody says I will pay the ערך erech of that person's
heart, that's essentially saying their entire ערך. erech. But if you say
the ערך erech of their leg or their arm, then you don't
pay anything. נפשות, Nefashot, now we have another דרשה. drasha. נפשות ולא
המת. Nefashot velo hamet. Now
if this person is dead, if you say the ערך erech of
a dead person, right, well, it's also male, female, this age, whatever.
No, it has to be נפש nefesh in the sense of life,
it has to be a living person. הוציא המת ולא הוציא את
הגוסס, Hotzi hamet velo hotzi et hagoses, maybe I'll only exclude a
dead person but I won't exclude a person that is, you know,
that is גוסס goses which is basically, you know, on his on
the deathbed about to die.
Exactly how הלכתית halachically we define גוסס, goses, but a person that
literally, you know, has a very short time left to live. תלמוד
לומר והעמיד והעריך. Talmud lomar ve'he'emid ve'he'erich.
It says the כהן will stand and evaluate. כל שישנו בהעמדה ישנו
בהערכה. Kol she'yeshno be'ha'amada yeshno be'ha'aracha. You might remember this, we had
this phrase before, ישנו בהעמדה ובהערכה. yeshno be'ha'amada u've'ha'aracha. Anybody that could
be stood up can be given a value. וכל שאינו בהעמדה, Ve'chol
she'eino be'ha'amada,
right, so the question is always how we define אינו בהעמדה. eino
be'ha'amada. So that's a question sometimes by animals even if they've been
שחט, shachted, we say it's ישנו בהעמדה yeshno be'ha'amada if they're still
alive. So the גמרא Gemara. is not always very rigorous or consistent
in terms of how it defines what's in or not in that
category of העמדה והערכה. ha'amada ve'ha'aracha. But here it's and also but
here the גמרא Gemara there's also a problem that this פסוק pasuk
is talking more about the person evaluating the person's ability to pay,
not the object that the person took the ערך erech obligated himself
for the ערך. erech.
You can say that it's not a problem because it's not really
meant to exclude.
Yeah, exactly. I mean the גמרא Gemara decides what to include or
exclude at this. וכל שאינו בהעמדה אינו בהערכה. Ve'chol she'eino be'ha'amada eino
be'ha'aracha. Somebody that cannot be stood up cannot be paid. So therefore
if even if you say the value of a person that's on
the deathbed, about to die, you also would not pay the ערך.
erech. Okay, that's another thing we learn out. דבר
אחר, נפשות, davar acher nefashot,
souls. אין לי אלא שאחד העריך אחד. Ein li ela she'echad he'erich
echad. I only know if you say one person's ערך. erech. אחד
שהעריך מאה מנין? Echad she'he'erich me'ah minayin? How do I know if
you did a hundred? תלמוד לומר נפשות. Talmud lomar nefashot. נפשות nefashot,
*nefashot*. Now תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* says the question is not if I
said ערך Erech, *erech* of John is on me and ערך Erech,
*erech* of Susan and the ערך Erech, *erech* of Paul. Obviously, some
good Jewish names. Obviously, those are... those would you obviously you'd pay
for. But let's say you said the ערך Erech, *erech* of ראובן
שמעון לוי יהודה Reuven Shimon Levi Yehuda *Reuven Shimon Levi Yehuda*. Okay,
so maybe since you only used the word ערך Erech *erech* once,
you only pay maybe the maximum of that, maybe you only pay
one ערך Erech, *erech*. No, you pay every, you pay for everybody
you mentioned. Okay. Now
the... so again we learn that from נפשות nefashot *nefashot* in the
plural. דבר אחר Davar acher, *Davar acher*, a lot of things we're
learning out from a few number of words, don't be bothered with
that economy of the words. Anyway, דבר אחר davar acher, *Davar acher*,
אין לי אלא איש שהעריך *Ein li ella ish shehe'erich*. I only
know if a man, it says, it says because the תורה Torah
*Torah* opens with the פסוק Pasuk *pasuk* about איש כי יפלי בערכך
beerkecha, נפשות nefashot? *Ish ki yafli be'erkecha nefashot*. So נפשות nefashot *nefashot*
which is generic is about the things, the people that are being
valued, the objects of the person's act, but not the people that
are doing the, that are taking the vow. So אין לי אלא
איש שהעריך בין איש בין אשה ein li ela ish sheheerich bein
ish bein isha. *Ein li ella ish shehe'erich bein ish bein isha*.
I only know if a man obligates himself to pay the value
whether it be man or woman, both men and women are on
the chart. אשה שהעריכה איש אשה שהעריכה אשה מנין *Isha shehe'ericha ish
isha shehe'ericha isha minayin*? How do I know if a woman undertakes
the vow to pay for a man or a woman? תלמוד לומר
*Talmud lomar* נפשות nefashot. *nefashot*. So it says נפשות nefashot *nefashot* which
again in the simple sense of the verse is the נפשות nefashot
*nefashot* are those that are being valued and that's how we used
the דרשה drasha. *drasha* before, but here we are using it to
say that even those that do the vow, בערכך beerkecha, נפשות nefashot
*be'erkecha nefashot*, the ערך Erech *erech* of the souls that undertook the
ערך Erech *erech*. So whether you are a man or woman. A
lot of different things we are learning out from these words. דבר
אחר davar acher, *Davar acher*, another thing we learn out, נפשות nefashot,
לרבות מנוול ומוכה שחין *nefashot lerabot menuval umuke shechin*. That's finally getting
to what we said in the beginning, that even somebody that is
disgusting and has no market value, you would still have the ערך
Erech *erech*, the fixed value the תורה Torah *Torah* assigns it. Okay,
שיכול *sheyachol*, I might have thought נדר בערכך כתיב neder be'erchecha ktiv,
*neder be'erkecha ketiv*, it says the vow with the ערך Erech, *erech*,
it links vowing with
ערך Erech *erech*. כל שישנו בערכין ישנו בדמים *Kol sheyeshno be'erchin yeshno
bedamim*, only somebody
that's on the
chart would be under, would be in
a נדר neder *neder*. וכל שאינו בערכין אינו בדמים *Vechol she'eino be'erchin
eino bedamim*, if you're not on the chart, then you wouldn't even
pay even if you obligated market
value. And since אנדרוגינוס androgynos. *androgynos* and טומטום tumtum *tumtum* are not
on
the
chart because they are not
clear, you know,
definite male, definite female, maybe even if you just said that I'll
pay their market value you wouldn't have to pay. תלמוד לומר והיה
ערכך v'haya erkecha, הזכר *Talmud lomar vehaya erkecha hazachar*. So it says
והיה ערכך הזכר *vehaya erkecha hazachar*, זכר ולא טומטום ואנדרוגינוס tumtum v'androgynous.
*zachar velo tumtum ve'androgynos*. Okay, so yes, it's true when it comes
to ערך Erech *erech*, it has to be clearly male, clearly female,
but when it comes to other things, it
does not, it is not limited that way. יכול לא יהא בערך
beerech, איש אבל יהא בערך אשה *Yachol lo yehei be'erech ish aval
yehei be'erech isha*, maybe it says הזכר *hazachar*, you need to be
definitely male to pay the male value, but somebody that's indeterminate gender
would pay the female value, maybe it would be male and anything
not male as opposed to male and female. תלמוד לומר והיה ערכך
הזכר ואם נקבה היא *Talmud lomar vehaya erkecha hazachar ve'im nekeva hi*.
So it says והיה ערכך הזכר *vehaya erkecha hazachar* and then it
says ואם נקבה היא *ve'im nekeva hi*. So ואם נקבה היא *ve'im
nekeva hi*, זכר ודאי נקבה ודאי *zachar vadai nekeva vadai*, only she
is a נקבה *nekeva* meaning a definite female. זכר ודאי נקבה ודאי
*Zachar vadai nekeva vadai*, only somebody that's a definite male, only somebody
that's a definite female, those are the only people you pay for
ערך Erech *erech*, ולא טומטום ואנדרוגינוס tumtum v'androgynous *velo tumtum ve'androgynos*, not
טומטום tumtum *tumtum* and אנדרוגינוס androgynos. *androgynos*. So a lot of הלכות
halachot. *halachot* of ערכין erchin. *erchin* we just quoted a major sort
of, you know, um, you know, like what's it called, a motherlode
of
מדרשי הלכה Halacha *midreshei halacha* to tell you a lot of different
הלכות halachot, *halachot* of ערכין erchin, *erchin* and now it goes on.
So can somebody give a market value to the Temple for a
טומטום?
tumtum, Yes, that's what it was saying. That even though they're not
in the category of ערך, Erech which is the fixed value the
Torah assigned, but you can actually, if you say דמיו עלי, Damav
Alai, I'll pay his value, market values, and you would pay him.
That's exactly the point, not to exclude and assume that it has
to be in both categories.
And can they do the evaluation?
Yes, and they definitely can do that was in the משנה. Right,
they can be the act of ערך, Erech they just can't be
the object of the ערך, Erech because that is because there we
only define by definite male, definite female. All right, let's take a
look at the גמרא. Gemara Now we're going to break this up
piece by piece. אמר מר בערכך לרבות ערך סתום. Amar Mar, Be'erkecha
lerabbot erech satum. Even if you just say an unexplicated ערך, Erech?
I'll pay the ערך Erech of a person. So, מאי ערך סתום?
Mai erech satum? What does this mean or how much do you
pay? דתניא האומר ערך סתום עלי, Detanya, ha'omer erech satum alai, if
somebody says
an unexplicated ערך, Erech it's unclear whether the word סתום Satum is
in the quote marks or not, or he says an ערך erech,
without explicating, either
way, נותן כפחות שבערכין. Noten kepachot shebe'arachin. You give the very
minimum. וכמה פחות שבערכין? Vekamma pachot shebe'arachin? What is the very minimum?
שלשה שקלים, Sheloshah shekalim, three shekels. If you look in the Torah,
a female infant the Torah says for ערך erech more than a
month is three shekels. So if he says I'll pay an ערך
erech and he doesn't say what, you assume you give the very
bare minimum of what that would be. So the גמרא Gemara says,
ואימא חמשים, Ve'eima chamishim, why not do the maximum? So, תפסת מרובה
לא תפסת תפסת מועט תפסת, Tafasta merubbah lo tafasta, tafasta mu'at tafasta,
a famous line the גמרא Gemara has, which is if you try
to grab too much you don't have it, if you grab a
little you get to keep
it. Exactly, like if somebody puts out food and at the table
and the kids
grab as much as they can, the mother might say you have
to put half of that back. But if you only take a
little bit, you'll get to keep what you take. So basically the
principle is that if you don't know how to interpret what the
הלכה halacha is, you assume that it at least has to be
the minimum. And that's how it's interpreted without any further indication that
it's at the minimum end. So anything more would include the three
shekels. Three shekels is the bare minimum, that's how we're going to
interpret it. So now the גמרא Gemara says,
ואימא שקל, Ve'eima shekel, maybe if you really want to say a
minimum, say one
shekel. דכתיב וכל ערכך יהיה בשקל הקדש, Dechtiv vechol erkecha yihyeh beshekel
hakodesh, that your value is in the shekel, and we said before
that that means that at the sliding scale the very bare minimum
is one shekel. So the גמרא Gemara says, ההוא בהשגת יד הוא
דכתיב. Hahu behasagat yad hu dechtiv. That's for when somebody can't afford
it. But if you can afford it, then the normal minimum is
three. Right, we only go lower if you can't meet the normal
amounts. But the normal minimum is three. So the גמרא Gemara says,
ואלא קרא למה לי? Ve'ala kra lamma li? So what's the פסוק
Pasuk. coming for? Meaning I wouldn't need a פסוק. Pasuk I could
have figured all that out by myself. If there was no extra
פסוק Pasuk and somebody just said ערך, erech I would by myself
figure out, okay, we have to assume the minimum
and I could have, what's the פסוק Pasuk telling me? Obviously I
would have come to that conclusion myself. So, אמר רב נחמן אמר
רבה בר אבוה לומר שאינו נידון בהשגת יד. Amar Rav Nachman amar
Rabbah bar Avuha, lomar she'eino nidon behasagat yad. Here's what the פסוק
pasuk. is telling you. That it is fixed at three, even if
the person is not able to afford it, his obligation is not,
for that person it's not a sliding scale. So, מאי טעמא? Mai
ta'ama? What's the reason? כמפורש דמי. Kemeforash dami. It's like you said
it explicitly. What does this mean? It means the following. It means,
this is the way תוספות explains it. It says like this. Look,
the way we're able to do the sliding scale is because you
didn't say explicitly how much you would have to pay. You said
I'm going to pay the ערך erech of ראובן. Reuven. So we're
going to take how much is the ערך erech. of ראובן? Reuven?
And it's like when you go to sell your car, I can
give you the Blue Book value, I can give you this value,
I can give you that value. I have a lot of books
I can refer to when you say the ערך erech of ראובן.
Reuven. So if you have the ability to pay, I'm going to
go to the standard, the Torah book value, the Blue Book value,
I'm going to say it's X. If you don't have the ability
to pay, I'll use a different book to estimate the value. Okay,
that's you give me the flexibility because you just say the ערך
erech of ראובן Reuven and you're not specific. But if you say
I'm going to pay ערך erech and you didn't say a certain
person, there's no way I can sort of say, well, what is
ערך erech or her ערך? erech There's nobody to evaluate what their
ערך erech is. You haven't given me any latitude. What we do
is we translate the words ערך erech without saying who as three
shekels, as if you said I'm going to give three shekels. So
therefore you haven't given me any latitude to make it less if
you can't afford it. That's the logic. If it's a specific person,
we can go through the act as if I'm assessing the value
of this particular person in front of me. But if it's no
particular person, it's just an abstraction, then there's nothing to assess. If
there's nothing to assess, then it's fixed at three and you don't
have that latitude. That's the logic that is being used here and
that's the חידוש Chiddush that when you just say it in the
generic way, you do not have a sliding scale.
What if you can't afford that?
Then it's an outstanding debt to the Temple, but the debt remains.
So the גמרא Gemara says... like this, and that's one explanation. But
now the גמרא Gemara says, איכא דאמרי, ika damri, some say, אמר
רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה, amar Rav Nachman amar Rabbah bar
Avuha, נידון דהשג יד, nidon dehesig yad, that it is dealt with
on the sliding scale and that's the חידוש, chidush, the opposite of
what we just said. פשיטא, obviously? No, מהו דתימא, mahu detema, I
might have thought exactly like I said a minute ago, כי מפרש
דמי, ki mefaresh dami, that when you do it in the generic
way, it's like you said explicitly three שקל shekel and you don't
have any latitude. קמשמע לן, kamashma lan, tells me no, since you
did not say explicitly three שקל, shekel, you just said value, it
still gives us the ability to determine for you, here's what the
value is, it's only one שקל. shekel. Okay, so that's what we
learned out from the somebody who does not explicate, it's three, and
in the end the גמרא Gemara seems to say and even that
person would have a sliding scale. Now the גמרא Gemara goes
on, דמי איברים. demei evarim. So it
says, בערכך, beerkecha I'm sorry, I skipped a line. דבר אחר, בערכך,
beerkecha ערך כולו הוא נותן, erech kulo hu noten, you give the
full ערך, erech ואינו נותן ערך איברים, veino noten erech evarim, and
not just a limb. If you say the ערך erech of a
limb, it's like you said nothing. You have to say the ערך
erech. of an entire person. So the גמרא Gemara says, first it's
just got the question about the economy of word usage, you can
only use one word for one דרשה. drasha So the גמרא Gemara
says, והא אפיקתיה לערך סתום veha afiktei leerech satum or סתם, stam,
didn't you already use the word בערכך for the case of somebody
just said ערך erech generically? How can you use it now also
to tell me that it has to be the ערך erech of
a full person? So קרי ביה ערך בערכך. kari bei erech beerkecha.
No, there's extra letters. If it would have just said בערך, I
would have said that's coming to include an unexplicated ערך. erech, When
it says בערכך in the singular possessive, that's coming to emphasize that
of a full person, not of just a limb. Okay, so now
the
גמרא Gemara says, יכול שאני מוציא דבר שהנשמה תלויה בו, yachol sheani
motzi davar shehaneshama teluya bo, maybe even if you said a thing
that the life depends on, like the heart or the brain, that
maybe there also you would not pay? תלמוד לומר נפשות, talmud lomar
nefashot, souls. So we learn from נפשות nefashot, anything that the soul
is dependent on. So you don't pay an ערך erech. for a
limb, but you do pay an ערך erech if you mentioned the
limb or an organ that the life force depended on. Now you
know what else we learn from נפשות? nefashot. Another הנחה. hanacha. נפשות
ולא המת, nefashot velo hamet, not a dead person. והא אפיקתיה, veha
afiktei, didn't you already use the word נפשות nefashot, to tell me
an organ that the soul depends on? קרי ביה נפש נפשות. kari
bei nefesh nefashot. It's the plural. It could have said נפש, nefesh,
it says נפשות. nefashot. So both teaches me if you say an
ערך erech. of a vital organ and it tells me the person
has to be, the object of the ערך erech has to be
alive.
Funny because על כל נפשות מת לא יבא, al kol nafshot met
lo yavo, which means that, you know, it is called נפש nefesh
and specifically it says the opposite. I understand.
I understand. הוציא את המת ולא הוציא את הגוסס, hotzi et hamet
velo hotzi et hagoses, maybe I'll only exclude the dead person but
not the person on the deathbed? תלמוד לומר והעמיד והעריך. talmud lomar
vehe'emid veheerich. He has to be able to stand up and we
assume that a גוסס goses halachically is not considered in that category
of being stood up. So the גמרא Gemara says, אי הכי מת
נמי תיפוק ליה מוהעמיד והעריך. ei hachi met nami tipok lei mevehe'emid
veheerich. So I could have excluded a corpse by the same principle.
You can't stand up a corpse, right? You can't stand up on
his own a corpse. So why did you need נפשות nefashot, to
exclude a corpse? הכי נמי, hachi nami, the גמרא Gemara says you're
right, we really didn't need the word נפשות nefashot, to exclude a
corpse. ואלא נפש נפשות למה לי? veela nefesh nefashot lama li? So
what do I need the extra נפשות to teach me if it's
not the dead, the corpse, because the corpse I learn out that
he can't be stood up or he can't stand himself up certainly?
So the גמרא Gemara says, כדבעינן למימר לקמן, kidevainan lemeimar lekaman, what
we're going to get to because there's other דרשות drashot we make
from נפשות, so we'll have plenty of things to learn from it,
don't you worry. Okay, now דבר אחר, now we're going to talk
about some of the other things we learn from it. נפשות, אין
לי אלא אחד שהעריך אחד. ein li ela echad sheheerich echad. I
only know if you said the ערך erech, of one person. אחד
שהעריך מאה מנין? echad sheheerich mea minayin? How do I know if
I said the ערך erech, of ראובן שמעון לוי יהודה etc.? I'll
pay the ערך erech. for everyone in the room, right?
Or something like that.
You won't say, you pay for each one even if you only
used the word ערך erech. once. תלמוד לומר נפשות, talmud lomar nefashot,
souls, which means you even for multiple at one time. Okay, now
we've got that דרשה drasha from souls, multiple. But now we're going
to try to do yet learn something else yet from נפשות. דבר
אחר נפשות, davar acher nefashot, אין לי אלא איש שהעריך בין איש
בין אשה. I only know if a man is doing the ערך
erech whether the object is a man or a woman. אשה שהעריכה
איש ואשה שהעריכה אשה מנין? isha shehericha ish veisha shehericha isha minayin?
How do I know if a woman is the one doing the
vowing? תלמוד לומר נפשות, talmud lomar nefashot, souls, which is learned to
be in here as part of the subject, not the object. Okay,
so that's two things now we've learned from נפשות, multiple people and
the woman. And now we're going to learn a third thing. דבר
אחר נפשות, להביא מנוול ומוכה שחין, lehavi menuval umukei shechin, even somebody
that is disgusting that would not have a market value is still
in this category. So now we have three things we learn from
נפשות. So the גמרא Gemara, says, והא אפיקתיה להנך? veha afiktei lehanach?
How can you use it for the last one? You've already used
it for other things. The גמרא Gemara says, הנך לא צריכי קרא.
hanach lo tzrichi kra. You know what? We really didn't even need
a verse for the other things. מאי טעמא? mai taama? Why not?
שקול הוא ויבואו כולם. shakul hu veyavou kulam. It's all equal so
they all come together, which isn't the same that... Sometimes when the
גמרא Gemara cannot succeed in its economy of verses, what I'm calling
the economy of verses, right? You only have one דרשה drasha per
verse. Sometimes it does it by a slightly different letter. Could have
written this way, it wrote it that way. Sometimes it says actually
all of these are more or less, there's not one that's more
of a persuasive דרשה drasha than the other. So if this is
coming to include, you know, it's coming, it'll include all of these
cases because I can't pick between which of these is more implied
by the verse. They're all equally implied by the verse. There's not
one which is somehow either logically or based on the verse more
in the word than the other. So therefore I assume it's teaching
me all of these הלכות. So that's basically an out that doesn't
force us to, you know, limit ourselves to the economy of the
verses. Okay. Now the גמרא, Gemara so, שקול ויבואו כולם. shakul v'yavo'u
kulam. כי אצטריך קרא, ki itzrich kra, so when you, what you
need the verse for, meaning the extra נפשות, you know, what is
sort of the special דרשה that's not so obvious is למנובל ומוכה
שחין הוא דאצטריך. l'menubal u'mukat shchin hu d'itzrich. For the case of
מנובל ומוכה שחין menubal u'mukat shchin because there I would say if
you're not in the category of, you know, of what do you
call, I really would have wanted to exclude that guy. There's not
such a logic to have excluded the case of a hundred people
or to say a woman is excluded. There would, so therefore those
I can pretty much figure out by myself or I'm very ready
to learn it from the פסוק. pasuk But the guy that doesn't
have a market value, I might really think that that's a cut
off of the ערך. erech, Maybe there's some people, maybe you don't
like מנובל ומוכה שחין. menubal u'mukat shchin. Maybe it's somebody that's old
and ill and infirm and that you only have to pay, will
not be able to do any labor and it's only going to
cost in terms of support. That doesn't mean he can't do labor.
I understand, so give a different example. Don't give מנובל ומוכה שחין.
menubal u'mukat shchin. There are definitely slaves that are, would have been
more of an expense than a benefit. So I might have thought
that they are not in ערכין. erchin So there I really needed
a פסוק pasuk? for. Okay. Now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
We're evaluating their worth to people, not their worth to God. Absolutely.
And as I said, that's like obviously a disturbing thing about all
of this is the קשה kasheh discussion we're going to be having
in this, number one, if it was just like the ערך erech
that the תורה Torah, sets a fixed value, fine, you know, it's
what people say and it's a fixed value and that's it and
the תורה just gives a number. Although even there, and I've been
waiting for you to raise this, Rav Gutt, but this is a
real problem in the פסוקים. psukim. The woman's value is always less
on that scale than the man. But the other thing is that
it's always contrasted to or compared to the case of when you
don't say ערך erech. but you say דמיו עלי, damav alai, which
you do market value, which is, implies the whole slave market. So
the whole institution, number one, of the slave market, you know, we
just obviously had Martin Luther King Day the other day, you know,
and, and the whole sense of assigning a dollar value to people,
you know, this is all some way like the הלכה on the
one hand sort of acknowledges that you cannot really value, you know,
give a dollar value to people, but if you have to for
certain הלכות, you use the model of the slave market, but we're
not really saying that that's any objective way of determining anybody's value
to anybody other than just a way of assigning something, a dollar
thing to something that intrinsically transcends any of that. But nevertheless, it's
very disturbing every time we refer to that institution, both the slave
market, both the slave institution of slavery and the sense of assigning
dollar value to people. I totally agree that that has to be
said. Or their insurance, or their sense of insurance. Well, yeah, that's
the amount that a person can produce, a person's right. Yeah, yeah,
but again, but even, but the תורה, but, but that, yeah, but
to actually say the value of the person to make the person
an object and say the value as an object, not just what
they can produce, right. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara goes, so
let's just read a little bit more in the גמרא Gemara... here.
גמרא Gemara says like this. Now we get to טומטום tumtum. ואנדרוגינוס.
All right, as if everything here is a little challenging. והיה ערכך,
the ערך, erech לרבות טומטום ואנדרוגינוס לדמים. l'rabot tumtum v'androgynous l'damim. That
even that, that's like sort of the flip of the מנובל ומוכה
שחין. menubal u'mukat shchin. That's a person without a market value, nevertheless
has an ערך. erech. טומטום tumtum ואנדרוגינוס don't have an ערך erech
because they're not definite male, definite female, but they still would have
this market value if somebody would say I'll give their market value.
So the גמרא Gemara says דמים למה לי קרא? damim lama li
kra? Why do I need a פסוק? לא יהא אלא דמי דקלא.
lo yehei ela d'mei dikla. So let it be like, let them
be like a palm tree. Now, now meaning, so I could say
I'll give the value of my car to the בית המקדש. So,
you know, why would I think that being male or female should
it at all make a difference and that they have to be
in the category of ערכין, erchin right? I can give the value
of anything, person, object, anything to the בית המקדש. What would have
been the הוה אמינא hava amina there? Now it occurs to me
that there might be a subtle pun or not pun, but sort
of thing here about the palm tree because of all the plants
and because of all the plants and trees, palm trees actually come
in the male and female gender. People know about this? That there
are male palm trees and female palm trees actually in terms of,
you know, which ones like, whatever, etc. So I'm wondering if that's
a little, if, maybe not, but what are you, I hear what
you're saying about
the whole gender issue anyway.
So, so the גמרא... Gemara. The גמרא says let them, you know
of course you would pay a market value. So the גמרא says
אילו אמר דמי דקלא מי לא יהיב? Ilu amar dmei dikla mi
lo yahiv? If you said the value of a palm tree you'd
pay, so of course if you said their value you pay. Why
would I think to exclude that? So אמר רבא amar Rava לומר
שנידון בכבודו lomar shenidon bichvodo to tell me that they are judged
in their honor.
What does that mean? סלקא דעתך אמינא let's just read it.
נדר בערכך כתיב, it says the נדר with the ערך. כל שישנו
בערכין נידון בכבודו, kol sheyeshno be'erchin nidon bichvodo, if you're in the
category of ערכין erchin then you're in the category of your honor.
וכל שאינו בערכין אינו בכבודו, vechol she'eino be'erchin eino bichvodo, if you're
not, not. What does that mean? So what רש"י Rashi says it
means is there's a little debate in the ראשונים Rishonim what it
means, but רש"י Rashi says it means is this idea before that
if you say a limb, כבודו kvodo means sort of like a
limb that represents your entire person, your entire person, meaning like your
heart, you know a vital organ, your brain, your kidneys, whatever, a
vital organ. So how do we know that if I say a
person's, how do I know that a vital organ represents the whole
person? We learned it out by ערכין erchin from the word נפשות,
soul. So if I say this person's heart, I'll pay the ערך
of his heart, we pay the entire ערך, it's like the whole
person. So now how do we know that it's not only true
by ערכין erchin. but it's also true by a straight valuation? If
I say I will pay the value, not the ערך, but the
market value of this person's heart to the בית המקדש, how do
you know you estimate the entire value of the person so that
you don't just sort of sum it and say well that's the
heart, that's not the liver, lungs, and you know everything else? How
do I know that the heart represents the entire person? That's what
the word כבודו kvodo means even for market value, not just for
ערך. That's learned out from what we find by ערך. So therefore
I might have said, ah, so if you're in the category, now
by the way this gets us out of the palm tree issue
because this is only about people. So therefore I might have said
if you're in the category of ערך then we can use vital
organs represents your entire person when it comes to market value. But
if you're not in the category of ערך, since that's where we
learn it all out from, then if I say this person's heart
for market value I would not pay their entire value. So that's
what the הוה אמינא hava amina would have been. You're right, if
I would have just said palm tree, car, anything, I give the
value. But what if you just said heart of a person? That
I learn out from ערכין erchin and that I might be limited
to people that are in the category of ערך and not טומטום
tumtum and אנדרוגינוס. Let's say this person's the best musician in the
world and I say the value of the hand, that represents the
whole person? Okay, but there's some value to the rest of them.
So the point is I might have thought that you do not
have it represent everything, you sort of, you actually make it somewhat
proportional to you know how that contributes to the entirety of the
person. How do I know, right? I mean there's a lot of
vital organs. If there are ten vital organs, each vital organ maybe
represents a tenth of the person. I might have come up with
some other calculus. How do I know to make the vital organ
being the whole value? I learn that from ערך. And therefore the
הוה אמינא hava amina is I would have limited it to people
who are in the category of ערכין. erchin? Yes. We're saying if
it's not in the category of ערך we can't apply it to
the market value? If it's not in the category of ערכין maybe
I cannot say that when I have a vital organ representing an
entire person, that would not apply in cases of market value. But
you said just before that you could apply the market value to
a טומטום tumtum. and אנדרוגינוס. Yes, but let's say I said the
heart of this טומטום, I will pay the market value of this
heart of this טומטום. I might say well it's not the entire
value of the טומטום because you only said the heart. How do
I know that to use the heart to represent the whole value
based on what I know from ערכין? But this טומטום is not
in ערך. So maybe it's some different calculus rather than paying for
the entire value of the טומטום. Is that clear? If you said
heart. If I said heart. That's the issue, if I said heart.
If I said the entire person or if I said this palm
tree, of course I pay the market value. But how do I
know if I say heart to represent the whole value? That is
the issue. These aren't taken contextually is what I'm saying. Right, right.
Well they might, let's take a look at the גמרא. אמר ליה
אביי, Amar lei Abaye, וכל שאינו בערכין אינו נידון בכבודו? ve-chol she'eino
be'erchin eino nidon bichvodo? Abaye says one minute, who says that's right?
There are cases that somebody is you know is not an ערך
and we don't represent the entire value of the person. How do
you know? והתניא, ve-hatanya, we'll just I guess have to end with
this ברייתא, braita, we'll read it. ראש עבד זה הקדש, Rosh eved
zeh hekdesh, הוא והקדש שותפין בו. hu ve-hekdesh shutafin bo. The head
of this slave is הקדש, hekdesh, it's not that הקדש hekdesh owns
the entire slave, you're partners with הקדש. hekdesh. Or if you say
ראש עבד מכור לך, rosh eved machur lach, the head of a
slave is sold to you, you haven't sold him the whole slave,
you're partners. ראש חמור זה הקדש, Rosh chamor zeh hekdesh, הוא והקדש
שותפין בו, hu ve-hekdesh shutafin bo, you're partners. ראש חמור מכור לך,
Rosh chamor machur lach, or you sell somebody the head of a
donkey, משמנין ביניהם, meshamnin beineihem, you evaluate it and you split it.
ראש פרה מכור לך, Rosh parah machur lach, however if you say
the head of a cow, לא מכר אלא ראשה, lo machar ela
roshah, then you're not really partners with somebody, then you just own
the head. Why does head really mean literally head? So ואמר רב
פפא, ve-amar Rav Papa, דחמיזדבן רישא דתורא בבית מטבחיא, de-hamizdaban reisha de-tura
be-veit matbachaya, because people in a, did I skip a line? אלא
ראש פרה... לא עוד אלא אפילו ראש פרה הקדש lo od ela
afilu rosh parah hekdesh אין קדוש אלא ראש פרה ein kadosh ela
rosh parah even if you sanctify the head you don't say you're
equal partners it's only the head. Why does that mean only the
head? ואמר רב פפא דהא מזדבין רישא דתורא בבית טבחא ve'amar Rav
Pappa deha mizdavin reisha detora beveit tavcha because when you go to
a butcher you can buy just the head so there head means
literal. But what do we see by all of this? When it
doesn't mean literal it means that you're split owners. So we actually
say we don't say this we say when you say somebody's thing
that it actually does not represent their entire it actually makes you
joint owners and we will pick up with this question tomorrow. When
you say somebody's head somebody's heart somebody's lungs are הקדש hekdesh are
I obligate myself to pay their value does it represent their whole
value or does it mean part of their value? We will continue
with that tomorrow. Okay.